Arthur S. Winchester papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Arthur S. Winchester Papers
1871-1901
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Winchester, Arthur S.
1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
The bulk of the collection, which is organized chronologically and also by author, consists of letters written and received by Arthur S. Winchester
Biographical Sketch
Arthur St. Claire Winchester was born on May 23rd, 1838 in South Windham, Connecticut to Harvey and Emily (Smith) Winchester. Harvey was a paper-machine manufacturer with the Smith & Winchester Corporation. Arthur had one brother, Edgar Clinton, who was born on September 6th, 1847. After their father's death in 1884, Arthur and Edgar continued in the paper-machine manufacturing business for a time.
Arthur was named a director of the Connecticut General Life Insurance Company in May of 1877. He was President of the Sharps Rifle Company in Bridgeport, Connecticut, before becoming treasurer for the Lee Arms Company (also in Bridgeport). He served in that capacity from at least 1899 through 1892 and continued to be involved with the company through the 1890s. He travelled extensively to England to further the company's business dealings there. He was also president of the Houston Institute and the New England Houston Narcotic Cure Company, both located in South Windsor, Connecticut.
Arthur married Annette Pamela Bingham in 1878. She died in 1880. The two had no children. Arthur died on January 11th, 1925. Edgar married Mary Gregg Wallace in 1890; the two had a son, Wallace, in 1894, but he died in 1895. Mary died in 1898. Edgar's date of death is unknown. According to Arthur's obituary, he lived at the Mohican Hotel in New London, Connecticut for 21 years until his death at 86.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection, which is organized chronologically and also by author, consists of letters written and received by Arthur S. Winchester. The earliest documents in the collection date from 1871 and the latest to 1901. Much of the collection is made up of letters written by Arthur to his brother, Edgar, between 1884 and 1897. General correspondence written by various individuals precedes letters arranged by author. These letters, primarily business related, were written to Arthur by C.M. Dally, James P. Lee, Charles Saunders and Edward G. Westcott.
In addition to the correspondence, the collection contains many documents relating to the Lee Arms Company, including coded telegrams and a lengthy transcription of coded communication between Arthur, James P. Lee, C.M. Dally and others. James P. Lee and the Lee Arms Company were at one time partnered with E. Remington and Sons. Invoices and correspondence from Remington can be found in this collection along with court documents pertaining to a lawsuit between the State of New York and E. Remington and Sons.
Patent documents in the collection, many in French or Italian and dating mostly between 1871 and 1878, appear to be research material for the Lee Arms Company or represent patents they hoped to or did purchase. Many of these patents are in the name of a Mr. King. Of particular interest are a series of documents related to E.L. Zalinski and the transfer of his fuse patent.
Letters from Edwin L. Palmer and J.S. Parsons, relating to the New England Houston Narcotic Cure Company, indicate the wide-ranging interests of Arthur Winchester. He was an officer in the company. Finally, personal bills of Arthur, Edgar and Harvey Winchester and papers relating to Harvey's estate are arranged at the end of the collection.
Materials are organized into a single series, Correspondence and Papers.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is open, but additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Winchester, Edgar; Dally, C.M.; Lee, James P.; Saunders, Charles; Palmer, Edwin L.; Winchester, Arthur S., 1838-1925; Winchester, Harvey; Winchester, Edgar; Dally, C.M.; Lee, James P.; Saunders, Charles; Palmer, Edwin L.; Winchester, Harvey
Corporate Names
Lee Arms Company; E. Remington & Sons; Sharps Rifle Manufacturing; New England Houston Narcotic Cure Company
Subjects
Correspondence; Patents.
Contents:
- I. Correspondence and Papers
  - General Correspondence to Arthur, 1878-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1898-1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - James P. Lee Correspondence to Arthur, 1892-1896 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester from Arthur, January 1884 -- March1888 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, June 1888 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, July 1888 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, August 1888 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, September 1888 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, October 1888 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, November 1888 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, December 1888 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, January 1889 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, February1889 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, March1889 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, October -November 1889 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, November -December 1889 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, January 1890 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, February1890 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, March1890 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, April 1890 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester May 1890 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester from Arthur, June 1890 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, July 1890 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, August 1890 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, January 1891 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, February1891 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters to E.C. Winchester, 1892 1897 Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Charles Saunders Correspondence to Arthur, 1889 May -July 1892 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Charles Saunders Correspondence, August -October 1892 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Charles Saunders Correspondence, November -December 1892 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Charles Saunders Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence to Arthur, 1891-1892 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, January -May 1893 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, June -August. 1893 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, September -December 1893 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, January -July 1894 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, August -December 1894 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, January -March1895 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, April -May 1895 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, January -December 1895 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, January -May 1896 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, June -September 1896 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, October -December 1896 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, January -March 1897 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Edward G. Westcott Correspondence, April -December 1897Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - C.M. Dally Correspondence to Arthur, 1889-1891 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - C.M. Dally Correspondence, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - C.M. Dally Correspondence, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - C.M. Dally Correspondence, 1894-1896 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hartley & Graham Correspondence, 1891-1892 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - J.W. Frazier Correspondence, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - A.C. Earle, Jr. Correspondence, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Coded Telegrams, 1887-1888 1890 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Telegram/Cable Transcript, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lee Rifle Documents, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Lee Arms Company Financial and Legal Documents, 1887-1898 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Financial Receipts and Statements, 1886-1898 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Willimantic Savings Institute Documents, 1885 1887 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Remington Invoices, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Remington Correspondence, 1886-1889 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - E.L. Zalinski Transfer of Fuse Patent Documents, 1886-1887 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Letters Patent and Patent Documents to Mr. King, 1871-1878, 1886, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Non-family related Documents (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Harvey Winchester Estate Papers, 1886-1896 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Arthur Winchester Personal Bills, 1870s-1880s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Arthur Winchester Personal Bills, 1890s-1900s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Edgar Winchester Personal Bills, 1870s-1880s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Edgar Winchester Personal Bills, 1890s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Harvey Winchester Personal Bills, 1860s-1870s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Harvey Winchester Personal Bills, 1880s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Winchester Family Bills, 1880s-1890s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Non-family Bills, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence, General1885-1902 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Edgar C. Palmer Correspondence, ca. 1893-1894 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - J.S. Parsons Financial Documents, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - J.S. Parsons Correspondence, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - J.S. Parsons Correspondence, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - J.S. Parsons Correspondence, ca. 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Houston Institute Financial Documents, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 16)